A Guide to the M. Caldwell Butler Papers 1945-2006
Lewis F. Powell, Jr. Archives, Washington and Lee University
Lewis F. Powell, Jr. Archives, School of Law, Washington and Lee University
M. Caldwell Butler Papers 1945-2006
Lewis F. Powell, Jr. Archives, School of Law, Washington and Lee University
004
This collection consists of ca. 93 cubic feet of materials.
Administrative Information
Access
The Ford medical and financial records are closed.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the library by M. Caldwell Butler in 1980-1983,1997,1999, 2004 and by his estate in 2015.
Biographical/Historical Information
Manley Caldwell Butler was born June 2, 1925 in Roanoke, Virginia, where he lived most of his life until his death on July 28, 2014. He received his A.B. from the University of Richmond in 1948 and his J.D. from the University of Virginia Law School in 1950. Butler married June Nolde in 1950. This union produced four sons: Manley, Henry, James and Marshall.
Butler served as the City of Roanoke Representative in 1960-1961. In 1962 he was elected to the Virginia House of Delegates. He was elected Minority Leader in 1966, a position he held until 1972 when he was elected to the 92nd U.S. Congress from the 6th District of Virginia. Butler served the 6th District for a decade. While serving on the Judiciary Committee, Butler participated in the impeachment action against President Richard M. Nixon during the summer of 1974. In the aftermath of Nixon's resignation, Butler was involved in the confirmation hearings of Gerald R. Ford and Nelson Rockefeller to serve as President and Vice President respectively. Butler was a principal architect of the Bankruptcy Reform Act of 1978. He was also a member of the Committee on Government Operations. In retirement, Butler served on the National Bankruptcy Review Commission in the years 1995-1997.
A partner in the firm of Woods, Rogers & Hazelgrove of Roanoke, Virginia from 1983-1998, Mr. Butler held memberships in the American Bar Association, the Virginia State Bar, the Roanoke Bar Association, the American College of Bankruptcy, the Raven Society, the Order of the Coif, and the Board of Directors of Dominion Bank Shares Corp of Roanoke. He was also a Fellow of the American Bar Foundation and a Director of the American Bankruptcy Institute. His fraternal organization affiliations include Phi Beta Kappa, Tau Kappa Alpha, Omicron Delta Kappa and Phi Gamma Delta.
Scope and Content Information
The M(anley)Caldwell Butler Papers consist of approximately 93 cu. ft. of materials from 1945-2006. Most of the papers cover the periods 1972-1982 and 1995-1997. The papers are divided into sixteen series: correspondence and subject files; military service; appointment calendars; campaigns; June Nolde Butler papers; scrapbooks, clippings and photos; speeches; newsletters, press releases, radio reports and weekly reports; voting record; constituency correspondence; confirmation of Gerald R. Ford as Vice President; impeachment of President Richard M. Nixon; Bankruptcy Reform Act of 1978; Legal Services Corporation; re-authorization of the Department of Justice for the Fiscal Year 1982; Voting Rights Act extension; and the National Bankruptcy Review Commission, 1995-1997. With the exceptions of the first six series and National Bankruptcy Review Commission materials, these papers were generated during Butler's terms as U. S. Representative for the 6th Congressional District of Virginia, 1972 -1982 (93rd Congress - 97th Congress).
The refinement levels of processing are mixed. The gradual donation of materials over a period of 35 years is chiefly the cause. The Nixon Impeachment and Bankruptcy Reform Act of 1978 materials are mostly described down to the folder level. The National Bankruptcy Review Commission materials arrived largely self-arranged. Most other areas of the colleciton, however, are largely unprocessed beyond being sorted into tentative series.
Contents List
- Correspondence 1973-1982, .5 cu. ft. (Carton 1)
- Subject Files, 1973-2004 (Carton 2)
  Subjects include: United States Court of Appeals for the Fourth Circuit; National Bankruptcy Review Commission; Sarah Butler Memorial; Sam Garrison Bar Discipline; Jefferson High School Reunions; World War II Service Records; Bankruptcy Law; Watergate/Impeachment; Susan Aheron; Butler for Governor; Newspaper Items; Legal Services Corporation; The Miller Center; and Virginia Cares.
- Appointment Calendars 1972-1982, 1 cu. ft. (Carton 3)
- Campaigns 1961-1983, 2 cu. ft. (Carton 4-5)
  Correspondence, subject files, surveys, election returns, and memorabilia
- June Nolde Butler c.1962-1977, 1 cu. ft. (Carton 6)
  Letters, diaries, notes, polical materials, Christmas cards,invitations, menus, photos and memorabilia of Butler's wife.
- Scrapbooks c.1961-2001, 13 cu. ft.
  - Assembled by June Nolte Butler c.1961-2001 (Carton 7-10)
  - 1973 Unknown Source (Carton 11)
  - Assembled by Butler's Father 1958-1969 (Carton 12-13)
  - Assembled by Congressional Staff 1958-1976 (Carton 14-18)
    In addition to campaign and general coverage, these scrapbooks treat: editorials mentioning Butler; economic conferences; farm conferences; HUD and FMHA conferences; Lynchburg Weather Station; minority business conferences.
  - Loose Clippings, c. 1977-1999 (Carton 19)
- Photos and Moving Images, 3 cu. ft.
  - Photo Albums, 1972-2004 (Carton 20-21)
    Most of these appear to have been kept by his Congressional Office Staff. They document his day-to-day official activities.
  - Photos, c. 1975-1982 (Carton 22)
    These also document his official activities.
  - Videotapes and Audiotapes, c. 1974-1999, Three 7" reels of acetate audiotape and six VHS videotapes. (Carton 22)
    The recordings range from appearances on Face the Nation to local forums.
- Printed Materials 1962-1998, 1.5 cu. ft. (Carton 22-23)
  There is a variety of publications on a variety of mainly political topics. forms of materials include trade books, government documents, brochures, and magazinies.
- Speeches 1973-1982, 4 cu. ft. (Carton 25-28)
  Speeches(1964-2001; bulk 1973-1982) are also arranged chronologically. The audience, occasion, and location are usually noted. From January 1976 onward, a topical index is present in addition to the chronological listings that are available for all of the years. Some nine speeches are missing from the original inventory, while others not on that listing were found during processing and added to the finding aid.
- News Letters, News (Press) Releases, Radio Reports, Weekly Reports 1972-1982, 2 cu. ft.
  Newsletters(1973-1981)were generated by Congressman Butler's staff to keep citizens of the Sixth District of Virginia informed on issues before the House, and on the activities of his office. The newsletters(N:) are arranged chronologically with an alphabetical reference index that has been updated through October 1, 1982. This index includes references to Radio Reports(RR#) and Weekly Reports(WR#). News (Press) Releases (1972-1982), Radio Reports (1973-1978), and Weekly Reports (1979-1982) are arranged chronologically and their indices provide brief summaries of the topics discussed.
  - Newsletters 1973-1981 (Carton 29)
  - News (Press) Releases (Carton 30)
    - Index
    - Releases 1972-1982
  - Radio Reports (Carton 30)
    - Index 1973-1978
    - Reports 1973-1978
  - Weekly Reports (Carton 30)
    - Index
    - Reports 1979-1982
- Voting Records 1973-1982, .5 cu. ft.
  The Members Personal Voting Record covers the period 1973-1982 (93rd Congress First Session to the 97th Congress Second Session). Each Congress' voting record is divided into two sessions. A cumulative record for each Congress is also present. Included here are: roll numbers, dates, daily record page number, description, and members response. Each record contains a roll call subject guide and an index to the voting record. Although Butler began his congressional term with the 92nd Congress, there is no personal voting record for this time.
  - Individual Voting Record (Carton 31)
    - 93rd Congress (Carton 31)
      - 1st Session 1973 (Carton 31)
      - 2nd Session 1974 (Carton 31)
    - 94th Congress (Carton 31)
      - 1st Session 1975 (Carton 31)
      - 2nd Session 1976 (Carton 31)
    - 95th Congress
      - 1st Session 1977 (Carton 31)
      - 2nd Session 1978 (Carton 31)
    - 96th Congress (Carton 31)
      - 1st Session 1979 (Carton 31)
      - 2nd Session 1980 (Carton 31)
    - 97th Congress (Carton 31)
      - 1st Session 1981 (Carton 31)
      - 2nd Session 1982 (Carton 31)
  - Roll Call Subject Guide (Carton 31)
    - 93rd Congress (Carton 31)
      - 1st Session 1973 (Carton 31)
      - 2nd Session 1974 (Carton 31)
    - 94th Congress (Carton 31)
      - 1st Session 1975 (Carton 31)
      - 2nd Session 1976 (Carton 31)
    - 95th Congress
      - 1st Session 1977 (Carton 31)
      - 2nd Session 1978 (Carton 31)
    - 96th Congress (Carton 31)
      - 1st Session 1979 (Carton 31)
      - 2nd Session 1980 (Carton 31)
    - 97th Congress (Carton 31)
      - 1st Session 1981 (Carton 31)
      - 2nd Session 1982 (Carton 31)
- Constituent Correspondence 1973-1975, 6 cu. ft.
  The Constituency Correspondence is almost exclusively from the period of the impeachment of Richard M. Nixon. The letters are divided into those favoring impeachment and those opposed to this action. There is also correspondence in reaction to the pardon of Nixon by President Gerald R. Ford.
  - Constituent Questionaires (Carton 32)
  - Impeachment of President Nixon (Carton 33-35)
    - Against
    - For
  - Pardon of President Nixon (Carton 36)
- Confirmation of Gerald R. Ford as Vice President; Confirmation of Nelson A. Rockefeller as Vice President 1973-1974, 1 cu. ft.
  Materials concerning the Confirmation of Gerald R. Ford as Vice President include: correspondence, memoranda, a briefing book, and transcriptions of testimony and proceedings during the hearings.
  Ford medical and financial records are closed.
  - Ford (Carton 37)
    - Correspondence & Memoranda (Carton 37)
    - Statements (Carton 37)
    - Voting Record (Carton 37)
    - Witness List (Carton 37)
    - Testimony (Carton 37)
    - Justice William O. Douglass Impeachment (Carton 37)
    - Printed Materials (Carton 37)
      - Photocopied articles
      - House of Reps. Report
    - Congressional documents (Carton 37)
      - Applications of the Twenty-Fifth Amendment to Vacancies in the Office of the Vice President, Legislative History, House Judiciary Committee, November 1973.
      - Nomination of Gerald F. Ford to be the Vice President of the United States, Hearing before House Judiciary Committee, November 1973.
  - Rockefeller -- Congressional printed documents (Carton 37)
    - Confirmation of Nelson A. Rockefeller as Vice President of the United States, 93rd Congress, House Report No. 93-1609, December 17, 1974. (Carton 37)
    - Analysis of the Philosophy and Public Record of Nelson A. Rockefeller, Nominee for Vice President of the United States, House Judiciary Committee, October 1974. (Carton 37)
    - Examination of vice President Designate Nelson A. Rockefeller's Tax Returns and other Financial Records, House Judiciary Committee & Senate Committee on Rules and Administration, October 1974. (Carton 37)
    - Nomination of Nelson A. Rockefeller to be Vice President of the United States, House Judiciary Committee, November 1974. (Carton 37)
    - Selected Issues and the Positions of Nelson A. Rockefeller, Nominee for Vice President of the United States, House Judiciary Committee, November 1974. (Carton 37)
- Impeachment of Richard M. Nixon 1973-1974, 15 cu. ft.
  Congressman Butler sat on the House Judiciary committee that investigated and voted on the impeachment of President Richard M. Nixon. The impeachment materials are 15 cu. ft. in extent and include: narratives about the Watergate break-in and related events, and about the bombing of Cambodia; interview transcripts and recorded testimony of persons involved in Watergate activities; general impeachment inquiry materials(committee notebooks, personal notes, etc.); reports on White House Surveillance activities; Department of Justice/ITT Litigation; Milk Producers Cooperatives investigations; papers re the Judiciary Committee's "Fragile Coalition"; general correspondence and memoranda; and printed materials. (See also, the series of constituent correspondence that precedes the impeachment materials. Butler kept an audio diary during the impeachment process, and these cassette recordings are included here, as are his written notes from this time. Also present are partial transcripts of an oral history project on the "Fragile Coalition" conducted in 1974.
  - Evidence and Research Materials
    - House Judiciary Committee Documents, Statements of Information before the Committee for the Judiciary, (LOOSE)
      - Events prior to Watergate Break-in (Carton 38)
        - Book I December 2, 1971- June 17, 1972 (Carton 38)
      - Events following Watergate Break-in (Carton 38)
        - Book II June 17, 1972 - February 9, 1973 (Carton 38)
        - Book III June 20, 1972-March 22, 1973 (Carton 38)
      - Events following Watergate Break-in (Carton 39)
        - Book III June 20, 1972-March 22, 1973 (Carton 39)
        - Book IV March 22, 1973-April 30, 1973 (Carton 39)
      - Book V: Testimony of Richard Kleindienst re:ITT (Carton 40)
      - Book VI: Political Contributions pledged by Milk Producers 1969-1972 (Carton 40)
      - Book VII, Vols. I-VI: Domestic Surveillance Activities directed by the White House (Carton 41)
      - Book VII, Vols. VII-VIII: Domestic Surveillance Activities directed by the White House (Carton 42)
      - Book VIII: Alleged White House attempts for IRS (Carton 42)
      - Book IX: Events following Watergate Break-in April 25, 1973-present (Carton 43)
      - Book IX: Events following Watergate Break-in April 25, 1973 - present (Carton 43)
      - Book XI: Bombing of Cambodia (Carton 43)
      - Book XII: Impoundment and Report of Government Expenditures on Nixon's Private Property (Carton 43)
    - Drafts/ Annotated, (LOOSE) (Carton 44)
      - Statements of Information without back-up evidence (Carton 44)
      - Book I: Events following Watergate Break-in June 19, 1972 - March 1, 1974 (Carton 44)
      - Book II: Department of Justice/ITT Litigation (Carton 44)
      - Book III: Political Contributions by Milk Producers Cooperatives: the 1971 Milk Price Support Decision (Carton 44)
      - Book IV: White House Surveillance Activities (Carton 44)
    - House Committee on the Judiciary: Index to Investigative Files compiled by the Impeachment Inquiry Staff May 9, 1974 (Carton 45)
      - Vol. I (Carton 45)
        - Background Information on White House Staff and Nixon's Campaign Organizations (Carton 45)
        - Correspondence (Carton 45)
        - Memoranda (Carton 45)
        - News Releases (Carton 45)
        - Resolutions (Carton 45)
        - "Constitutional Grounds for Presidential Impeachment" (Carton 45)
        - Organization (Carton 45)
        - Personnel: Biographical Materials (Carton 45)
        - Presentation Procedures for Impeachment Inquiry (Carton 45)
      - Vol. III (Carton 45)
        - Correspondence (Carton 45)
        - Memoranda (Carton 45)
        - Photocopied Documents (Carton 45)
    - Subject Files (Carton 45)
      - Printed Materials--miscellaneous pamphlets, law reviews, Congressional Records (Carton 45)
      - Judge John J. Sirica's Decision/Opinion re Transmission of Evidence to the House of Representatives (Carton 45)
      - Peter W. Rodino (Chairman, Committee on the Judiciary House of Representatives)Press Releases May 9, 1974 - July 12, 1974 (Carton 45)
      - Impeachment Briefing Books, I-III. Subpoena Material with Index (Carton 45)
        - Book II Subpoenas & Supporting Materials re taped conversations, daily diaries, IRS, ITT, Milk Price Support and Domestic Surveillance (Carton 45)
      - Bill Dixon Memoranda on Evidence-Brief summaries of Book 2 regarding the facts known concerning the 6/17/72 Watergate break-in (Carton 45)
      - Minority Memoranda on Article II (Carton 45)
      - Minority Memoranda on Facts & Law re President's receipt of information about the Watergate Grand Jury Investigation from Henry Petersen (Carton 45)
      - Summary of Information by Committee Staff (Carton 45)
        - Watergate (Carton 45)
        - Abuse of Presidential Powers (Carton 45)
      - Refusal of President to Comply with Subpoenas (Carton 45)
      - Willful Tax Evasion (Carton 45)
      - Impeachment Inquiry Staff:List of names and addresses June 1974 (Carton 45)
    - Presidential transcripts (Carton 46)
      - Reports, UHER 5000 Tape Recorder (Carton 46)
      - Analysis of Presidential Transcripts, with Index September 15, 1972 - April 27, 1973 (Carton 46)
      - Presidential Transcripts:Books 1-3, Nos. 1-49 1972-1973 (Carton 46)
      - Transcripts: Impeachment Inquiry Staff 1971-1973 (Carton 46)
        - Watergate (Carton 46)
        - Milk (Carton 46)
        - ITT (Carton 46)
        - Plumbers (Carton 46)
      - Comparison of White House and Judiciary Committee Transcripts of 8 Recorded Presidential Conversations May-June 1974 (Carton 46)
  - Records of Impeachment Inquiry Proceedings (Carton 47-48)
    - Draft Articles of Impeachment
    - Committee Proceedings on Articles of Impeachment
      - Impoundment
      - Taxes
      - Exhibits
      - Emoluments
      - Contempt
      - Articles I & II
    - Fragile Coalition Plans
    - Coalition Materials: Resolutions to Articles of Impeachment
    - Personal Notes (MCB)
    - House Judiciary Committee Hearings: U.S. Report of Proceedings held before the Committee on the Judiciary, Impeachment Inquiry: Stenographic Minutes May 22, 1974 - June 18, 1974; July 2, 1974 - July 30, 1974
      Unrevised and unedited
    - Analysis of Constitutional Standard for Presidential
    - Page Proofs for Judiciary Committee Report 1974
    - The EOB Tape of June 20, 1972: Report on a Technical Investigation Conducted for the U.S. District Court for the District of Columbia 1972
    - Joint Committee on Congressional Operations March 15, 1974
    - United States v. John N. Mitchell and United States v. Nixon and Nixon v. United States July 24, 1974
    - Submission of Recorded Presidential Conversations April 30, 1974
    - Judiciary Committee Proceedings/M. Caldwell Butler's Personal Notes April 1974 - August 1974
  - Printed Materials (Carton 49-53)
    The Printed Materials are primarily government documents from the period of the impeachment of Richard M. Nixon. Below is an enumeration of the titles present from donor gifts 1980-1983. Titles from additions, 1985-2015 are present in these boxes, but not yet listed below.
    - Congressional Documents
      - House Judiciary Committee Documents, Statement of Information before the Committee on the Judiciary, (BOUND) (Carton 49)
        - Events Prior to Watergate Break-in (Carton 49)
          Book I: December 2, 1971 - June 17, 1972
        - Events following Watergate Break-in (Carton 49)
          Book I: June 19, 1972 - March 1, 1974
          Book II: June 17, 1972 - February 9, 1973
        - Book II: Department of Justice/ITT Litigation (Carton 49)
        - Book III: Political Contributions by Milk Producers Cooperatives: The 1971 Milk Price Support Decision (Carton 49)
        - Events following the Watergate Break-in (Carton 49)
          Book III: June 20, 1972 - March 22, 1973
        - Book IV: White House Surveillance Activities (Carton 49)
        - Events following Watergate Break-in (Carton 50)
          Book IV: March 22, 1973 - April 30, 1973
        - Book V: Department of Justice/ITT Litigation Richard Kleindienst Nomination Hearings (Carton 50)
        - Book VI: Political Contributions by Milk Producers Cooperatives: The 1971 Mile Price Support Decision House Judiciary Committee Documents, Statements of Information before the Committee on the Judiciary, (BOUND) (Carton 50)
        - Book VII: White House Surveillance and Campaign Activities (Carton 50)
        - Book VIII: Internal Revenue Service (Carton 50)
        - Book IX: Watergate Special Prosecutors Judiciary Committee's Impeachment Inquiry (Carton 50)
        - Book X: Tax Deduction For Gift of Papers (Carton 50)
        - Book XI: Bombing of Cambodia (Carton 50)
        - Book XII: Impoundment of Funds Government Expenditures on Nixon's Private Properties (Carton 50)
        - Appendices (Carton 50)
          Appendix: Political Matters Memoranda
          I: Presidential Statements
          II: Papers in Criminal Cases
          III: Supplementary Documents
          IV: Political Matters memoranda
        - Senate Committee on the Judiciary Hearings "Special Prosecutor" Parts 1 & 2 October - November 1973, (Bound) (Carton 50)
        - Committee on Armed Services United States Senate "Bombing in Cambodia" July - August 1973, (Bound) (Carton 50)
        - Committee on the Judiciary United States Senate (Carton 50)
        - "Richard G. Kliendienst-Resumed" Parts 1 & 2 March-April 1972, (Bound) (Carton 50)
        - "Louis Patrick Gray III" February 1973 (Carton 50)
        - "Nomination of Elliot L. Richardson to be Attorney General" May 1973 (Carton 50)
        - Joint Committee on Internal Revenue Taxation Examination of President Nixon's Tax Returns for 1969-1972 (Carton 50)
        - Committee on the Judiciary House of Representatives (Carton 50)
        - Debate on Articles of Impeachment July 1974, (BOUND) (Carton 50)
        - Impeachment of Richard M. Nixon August 1974, (BOUND) (Carton 50)
        - Summary of Information July 19, 1974, (BOUND) (Carton 50)
        - Statement of Information: Background Memorandum May - June 1974, (BOUND) (Carton 50)
        - Testimony of Witnesses: Books I-III July 1974, (BOUND) (Carton 50)
        - Report by the Staff of the Impeachment Inquiry: Constitutional Grounds for Presidential Impeachment February 1974 (Carton 50)
      - Committee on the Judiciary - Statement of Information Submitted on Behalf of President Nixon- Book II, IV. (Carton 51)
      - Committee on the Judiciary - Brief on Behalf of the President of the United States. (Carton 51)
      - Committee on the Judiciary - Debate on Articles of Impeachment. (Carton 51)
      - Committee on the Judiciary - Impeachment Inquiry - Book I, II. (Carton 51)
      - Committee on the Judiciary - Minority Memorandum on Facts and Law. (Carton 51)
      - Impeachment - Selected Materials. (Carton 51)
      - Impeachment - Selected Materials on Procedure. (Carton 51)
      - Impeachment of Richard M. Nixon, President of the United States. (Carton 51)
      - Examination of President Nixon's Tax Returns for 1969 Through 1972. (Carton 51)
      - Constitutional Grounds for Presidential Impeachment, House Judiciary Committee February 1974 (Carton 51)
      - Court Proceedings and Actions of Vital Interest to the Congress, Joint Committee on Congressional Operations July 1974 (Carton 51)
      - Impeachment Inquiry Book II, House Judiciary Committee. November 1974 (Carton 51)
      - Inquiry in the Alleged Involvement of the Central Intelligence Agency in the Watergate and Ellsberg Matters, House Subcommittee on Intelligence. July 1974 (Carton 51)
      - Procedure and Guidelines for Impeachment Trials in the United States Senate, 93rd Congress, Senate Report No. 93-102 (Carton 51)
      - Transcript of Eight Recorded Presidential Conversations, House Judiciary Committee. May - June 1974 (Carton 51)
      - Presidential Campaign Activities of 1972: Books 1-17, 19-26 (Carton 52)
        Executive Session Hearings Before the Select Committee on Presidential Campaign Activities of the United States Senate, November 13,14,15,16, December 4, 11, 1973.